Fred Cazel Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Fred Cazel Papers
undated, 1939-1992.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Cazel, Fred A.
15.3 linear feet.
Fred Cazel was a professor in the History Department at the University of Connecticut from 1948-1988. He was active in many professional and University committees.
MSS19880006
Biography
Fred Cazel was a professor in the history department at the University of Connecticut from 1948-1988. He was actively involved in the Medieval Studies Program, as well as many organization, including Phi Beta Kappa and the Conference on British Studies. He was an active member of university committees, including presidential search, History Department and various university senate committees. He was president of the Senate Executive Committee for many years.
Scope and Content
The collection contains notes, correspondence and related materials pertaining to Professor Cazel's interests and activities. The papers focus mainly on the organizations, committees, programs and events with which he was involved and include files on AAUP, the Committee on Curricula and Courses, the Committee of Five to Investigate Charges of Communism, and the New England Historical Association. Also included are some research and teaching materials.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
University of Connecticut—Faculty—Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut, Dept. of History.; University of Connecticut. Medieval Studies Program.; University of Connecticut. University Senate. Executive Committee.; American Association of University Professors. University of Connecticut Chapter.; University of Connecticut. Committee of Five to Investigate Charges of Communism.; University of Connecticut. Committee on Curricula and Courses.; New England Historical Association.; Universities and colleges—Connecticut.; History—Study and teaching—Connecticut.; Connecticut—Education—Universities and colleges.
Document Types:
Notes.; Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Reports.; Publications.; Administrative Records
Occupations:
Educator.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The papers were donated by Professor Cazel to the University of Connecticut Libraries after his retirement in 1988. Additional materials were donated in 2002 and 2003 but have not yet been integrated into the collection.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Papers, undated, 1939-1992
  - American Association of University Professors, 1939-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1939-1962 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - 1960-1964 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1:, Folder 10-11)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 13-14)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - 1982 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - 1983 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
    - 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Self-Evaluation, 1966-1967 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - Annual Meeting, 1978 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - CT Conference, 1981 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - Constitution Committee, 1977-1978 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - Questionnaire on Research, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - Salary Proposal, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - State Conferences, 1961-1964 (Box 1:, Folder 27-28)
  - AAUP and Federation of University Teachers, 1965-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 29-31)
  - Academic Dismissals, 1973-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Acting President, Edward V. Gant, 1979 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Summer Session, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Patricio Incident: Freedom of Speech, 1971 (Box 2:, Folder 35)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on the Evaluation of the President, 1984 (Box 2:, Folder 36)
  - Admissions reports, 1974 (Box 2:, Folder 37)
  - Advisory Committee on Animal Care, 1981-1982 (Box 2:, Folder 38)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1974 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
  - AFL-CIO, undated (Box 2:, Folder 41)
  - All-University Advisory Committee on Gerontology, 1978-1979 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
  - American Historical Association, undated (Box 2:, Folder 43)
  - American Journal of Orthopsychology, 1971 (Box 2:, Folder 44)
  - Anniversary Committee, 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 45)
  - Articles—Grades New York Times, 1972 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
  - Arts & Sciences Committee on Curricula and Courses, 1962-1964 (Box 2:, Folder 47)
  - Arts & Sciences Committee on NEH Grant, undated (Box 2:, Folder 48)
  - Arts & Sciences Committee on Promotion, 1958-1959 (Box 2:, Folder 49-50)
  - ASG and FSSO, 1972-1974 (Box 2:, Folder 51)
  - Babbidge Center for Historical Studies and Chair in History, 1984 (Box 2:, Folder 52)
  - BGS Courses, 1980 (Box 2:, Folder 53)
  - Blue Book Revision Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 2:, Folder 54)
  - Briefing for the Board of Trustees, 1971 (Box 2:, Folder 55)
  - Board of Trustees meeting, 1979 (Box 2:, Folder 56)
  - Branches, undated (Box 2:, Folder 57)
  - Budget, 1979 (Box 2:, Folder 58)
  - Building Naming Committee, 1992 (Box 11)
  - Bureau of Educational Research, 1967-1968 (Box 2:, Folder 59)
  - By-Laws revision Committee, undated (Box 11)
  - By-Laws revision Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 2:, Folder 60-61)
  - Centennial, undated (Box 2:, Folder 62)
  - Civil Rights, 1972-1973 (Box 2:, Folder 63)
  - Collective Bargaining, 1974-1981 (Box 2:, Folder 64-66)
  - College of Arts and Sciences, 1948-1956 (Box 2:, Folder 67)
  - College of Liberal Arts & Sciences, 1966-1974 (Box 2:, Folder 68-69)
  - College Scholarship Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 2:, Folder 70)
  - Commencement, 1969-1974 (Box 2:, Folder 71-74)
  - Commencement Committee, 1975-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 75-78)
  - Commencement Committee, 1985-1987 (Box 3:, Folder 79-82)
  - Commission for Higher Education, 1972-1973 (Box 3:, Folder 83)
  - Committee against Racism, 1974 (Box 3:, Folder 84)
  - Committee of Five to Investigate Charges of Communism, 1953 (Box 3:, Folder 85-86)
  - Committee of Five—report, 1953 (Box 3:, Folder 87)
  - Committee of Three, 1974 (Box 3:, Folder 88)
  - Committee of Three/Committee of Five, 1968 (Box 3:, Folder 89)
  - Committee on Change and Innovation, 1975 (Box 3:, Folder 90)
  - Committee on the Cost of Instruction, 1973 (Box 3:, Folder 91)
  - Committee on Curricula and Courses, 1961-1975 (Box 3:, Folder 92-96)
  - Committee on Departmental Promotion, Tenure and Reappointment, 1981 (Box 3:, Folder 97)
  - Committee on Documentary reproduction, 1960-1963 (Box 3:, Folder 98)
  - Committee on Fellowships and Scholarships, 1962-1963 (Box 3:, Folder 99)
  - Committee on Nominations procedures, 1969 (Box 3:, Folder 100)
  - Committee on Ombudsman, 1981 (Box 3:, Folder 101-102)
  - Committee on Recruitment and replacement, 1967-1968 (Box 3:, Folder 103)
  - Committee on Reorganization of the Senate, 1973 (Box 3:, Folder 104)
  - Committee on Scholarship, 1969-1970 (Box 3:, Folder 105)
  - Committee on Scholastic Standards, 1971-1981 (Box 3:, Folder 106-108)
  - Comprehensive Committee, 1987-1988 (Box 3:, Folder 109)
  - Conference on British Studies, 1953-1977 (Box 3:, Folder 110-114)
    - CBS-New England Affiliate meeting, 1969 (Box 3:, Folder 115)
    - Executive Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 3:, Folder 116)
  - Conference on Higher Education and CT's Economy, 1982 (Box 3:, Folder 117)
  - Connecticut Academy of Arts & Sciences, 1964-1965 (Box 4:, Folder 118)
  - CT History—John Hay Fellows, 1963-1964 (Box 4:, Folder 119)
  - ConnPirg, 1972-1973 (Box 4:, Folder 120)
  - Controller's Office, 1972-1974 (Box 4:, Folder 121)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 4:, Folder 122-123)
  - Counseling and Testing Center, 1973 (Box 4:, Folder 124)
  - Course Credit by Examination, undated (Box 4:, Folder 125)
  - Course on the Bible, undated (Box 4:, Folder 126)
  - CUES II Student Survey, undated (Box 4:, Folder 127)
  - Curriculum, 1973 (Box 4:, Folder 128)
  - Curricular reform, 1979 (Box 4:, Folder 129)
  - Daily Campus, 1974 (Box 4:, Folder 130)
  - Distinction, 1960-1967 (Box 4:, Folder 131-137)
  - Ecclesiastical History Society, 1973 (Box 4:, Folder 138)
  - Emeritus Faculty/Retirement, undated (Box 4:, Folder 139)
  - Etherington Commission, undated (Box 4:, Folder 140)
  - European History Bobbs-Merrill reprint series, undated (Box 4:, Folder 141)
  - Experimental College, undated (Box 4:, Folder 142)
  - Faculty-Alumni Center>, 1970-1971 (Box 4:, Folder 143)
  - Faculty for Rational Alternatives, undated (Box 4:, Folder 144)
  - Faculty Scholarship program, undated (Box 4:, Folder 145)
  - Faculty Standards Committee, 1961-1983 (Box 4:, Folder 146-151)
  - Feminists, undated (Box 4:, Folder 152)
  - Financial Aid Committee, 1968-1970 (Box 4:, Folder 153-154)
  - Financial Aid Department, 1976-1986 (Box 4:, Folder 155-156)
  - Forecast of New Technology in Higher Education, 1972 (Box 4:, Folder 157)
  - Foreign Languages, 1954-1956 (Box 4:, Folder 158)
  - Fund for Advancement of Education Study, undated (Box 4:, Folder 159)
  - Goals and Needs Committee, 1974 (Box 4:, Folder 160)
  - Grading, undated (Box 4:, Folder 161)
  - Graduates—lists, 1967-1968 (Box 4:, Folder 162)
  - Graduate policies, undated (Box 4:, Folder 163)
  - Graduate program, 1970-1974 (Box 4:, Folder 164)
  - Graduate School, 1967-1971 (Box 4:, Folder 165-167)
  - Graduate School, 1972-1974 (Box 5:, Folder 168-169)
    - Executive Committee, 1982 (Box 5:, Folder 170)
    - Research Foundation, 1974 (Box 5:, Folder 171)
  - Graduate Student Council, 1972 (Box 5:, Folder 172)
  - Growth and Development Committee, 1971-1977 (Box 5:, Folder 173)
  - Hastings Nonacentennial, 1966 (Box 5:, Folder 174)
  - Higher Education, 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 175)
  - Higher Education of Blacks in the US, undated (Box 5:, Folder 176)
  - History Colloquium, 1960 (Box 5:, Folder 177)
  - History Department, 1948-1984 (Box 5:, Folder 178-189)
    - Annual report, 1974 (Box 5:, Folder 190)
    - Committee on Comprehensive Exams, 1988 (Box 5:, Folder 191)
    - Committee on Promotion, undated (Box 5:, Folder 192)
    - Committee on Undergraduate program, 1970 (Box 5:, Folder 193-195)
    - Courses, undated (Box 5:, Folder 196)
    - Minutes, 1966-1980 (Box 5:, Folder 197-198)
    - Newsletters, undated (Box 5:, Folder 199)
    - Promotion and Tenure Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 5:, Folder 200)
    - Publicity, undated (Box 5:, Folder 201)
    - Search Committee, 1986 (Box 6:, Folder 202)
    - Subcommittee on Supervised Teaching, 1970-1972 (Box 6:, Folder 203)
  - Honors program—pilot, 1965 (Box 6:, Folder 204)
  - Honors program, 1970-1971 (Box 6:, Folder 205)
  - Honors program report, 1969 (Box 6:, Folder 206)
  - Human Rights and Opportunities, 1968-1970 (Box 6:, Folder 207)
  - Inauguration, 1979 (Box 6:, Folder 208)
  - Inauguration Committee, 1985 (Box 6:, Folder 209)
  - Inner College Evaluation, undated (Box 6:, Folder 210)
  - Inner College program, undated (Box 6:, Folder 211)
  - Inquiry Update—, Southern Connecticut State College, 1974 (Box 6:, Folder 212)
  - Institute of Water Resources, 1970-1971 (Box 6:, Folder 213)
  - Inter-University Consortium for Political Research (ICPR), 1968 (Box 6:, Folder 214)
  - Irish Ireland Movement, undated (Box 6:, Folder 215)
  - Joint Policy Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 6:, Folder 216)
  - King Guest Professorship, 1979 (Box 6:, Folder 217)
  - Kramer School—course selection, undated (Box 6:, Folder 218)
  - LAAS Scholarship Committee—Woodrow Wilson Fellowship, 1969-1970 (Box 6:, Folder 219)
  - Law and By-laws, 1981, 1986 (Box 6:, Folder 220-221)
  - Lecture Notes (100-200 level), undated (Box 12:)
  - Legislative Laision, 1971-1972 (Box 6:, Folder 222)
  - Library, undated (Box 6:, Folder 223)
  - Library Advisory Committee, 1949-1966 (Box 6:, Folder 224-225)
  - Long Range Planning, 1975-1976 (Box 6:, Folder 226)
  - Long Range Planning Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 6:, Folder 227)
  - Lougee Memorial Committee, 1984 (Box 6:, Folder 228)
  - Mansfield Investment Club, 1975-1977 (Box 6:, Folder 229)
  - Master Plan, 1973 (Box 6:, Folder 230-232)
  - Master Plan article, 1974 (Box 6:, Folder 233)
  - Medievalists, 1966-1967 (Box 6:, Folder 234)
  - Medieval Studies, 1975-1982 (Box 6:, Folder 235)
  - Medieval Studies Committee>, 1968-1974 (Box 6:, Folder 236-240)
  - Medieval Studies Group, 1967-1972 (Box 7:, Folder 241-243)
  - Medieval Studies program—Graduate merit increases, 1967-1971 (Box 7:, Folder 244)
  - Metanoia Committee, undated (Box 7:, Folder 245)
  - Moore Testimonial Dinner, 1958 (Box 7:, Folder 246)
  - Munsun Institute Steering Committee, 1974 (Box 7:, Folder 247)
  - National Research Council, 1974 (Box 7:, Folder 248)
  - New England Association of Social Studies Teachers, 1953-1958 (Box 7:, Folder 249-250)
  - NEH Grant for History 100/101, 1984 (Box 7:, Folder 251)
  - NERAC, 1972 (Box 7:, Folder 252)
  - New England Historical Association, undated (Box 7:, Folder 253)
  - New England Historical Association, 1980-1981 (Box 7:, Folder 254-257)
  - New England Medieval Conference, 1980 (Box 7:, Folder 258)
  - Newspaper reprints, undated (Box 7:, Folder 259)
  - Nominating Committee—Correspondence, 1974 (Box 7:, Folder 260)
  - Northwood Apartments, 1984 (Box 7:, Folder 261)
  - Office of Research Development, 1979 (Box 7:, Folder 262)
  - Ombudsman, 1982 (Box 7:, Folder 263)
  - Patent Advisory Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 7:, Folder 264)
  - Personnel, 1981-1982 (Box 7:, Folder 265)
  - Ph.D. Committee, 1961 (Box 7:, Folder 266)
  - Phi Alpha Theta, 1965 (Box 7:, Folder 267)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1949-1982 (Box 7:, Folder 268-276)
  - Phi Kappa Phi, undated (Box 7:, Folder 277)
  - Physics, undated (Box 7:, Folder 278)
  - Placement Committee, 1970-1974 (Box 7:, Folder 279-280)
  - Placement and career planning, 1968-1972 (Box 7:, Folder 281)
  - Planning Coordination Committee, 1975 (Box 7:, Folder 282)
  - Pre-Legal Committee, undated (Box 7:, Folder 283)
  - President's newsletter, 1966-1970 (Box 8:, Folder 284)
  - President's office, 1969-1970 (Box 8:, Folder 285)
  - Presidential evaluation, 1984 (Box 8:, Folder 286)
  - Presidential search committee, 1972 (Box 8:, Folder 287)
  - Presidential search advisory committee, 1973, 1978 (Box 8:, Folder 288-289)
  - Professional courses, undated (Box 8:, Folder 290)
  - Professional Employees' Association, undated (Box 8:, Folder 291)
  - Promotion and Tenure, 1973 (Box 8:, Folder 292)
  - Provost's search committee, 1974 (Box 8:, Folder 293)
  - Provost's search committee correspondence, 1974 (Box 11)
  - Publications, pamphlets, serials, notes, undated (Box 8:, Folder 294-295)
  - Radio-TV Center, 1966 (Box 8:, Folder 296)
  - Records Scholarship Committee, 1962-1969 (Box 8:, Folder 297-298)
  - Registrar's Office, 1967-1974 (Box 8:, Folder 299)
  - Research Development Fact Sheets, 1970-1974 (Box 8:, Folder 300-301)
  - Research Development Office—Grant deadlines, 1979 (Box 8:, Folder 302)
  - Resumes and dossiers, undated (Box 8:, Folder 303)
  - Scheduling and staffing, 1973 (Box 8:, Folder 304)
  - Scholastic Standards Committee, undated (Box 8:, Folder 305)
  - Second Century Fund, undated (Box 8:, Folder 306)
  - Select Faculty Committee, 1967 (Box 8:, Folder 307)
  - Senate, undated (Box 8:, Folder 308)
  - Senate Bill 620, undated (Box 8:, Folder 309)
  - Senate Executive Committee, 1970-1973 (Box 8:, Folder 310-318)
  - Senate Executive Committee, 1973-1982 (Box 9:, Folder 319-341)
  - Senate Executive Committee, 1982-1984 (Box 10:, Folder 342-345)
    - Committee on Externally Funded Research and Instruction, 1973 (Box 10:, Folder 346)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 10:, Folder 347)
    - Governor's Commission on Higher Education, 1981 (Box 10:, Folder 348)
    - Master Plan, 1973 (Box 10:, Folder 349)
    - USSO Constitution, undated (Box 10:, Folder 350)
  - Senate Nominating Committee, 1971-1982 (Box 10:, Folder 351-358)
  - S.D.S., undated (Box 10:, Folder 359)
  - Service Center for Teachers, 1957-1958 (Box 10:, Folder 360)
  - Sigma Nu Alpha, 1963 (Box 10:, Folder 361)
  - Social Science Building, 1951 (Box 10:, Folder 362)
  - Social Science Data Center, 1972 (Box 10:, Folder 363)
  - Special Committee on Infirmary, 1964 (Box 10:, Folder 364)
  - Stamford Position, 1974 (Box 10:, Folder 365)
  - Student Dismissals, 1964 (Box 10:, Folder 366)
  - Student Evaluations, 1969-1988 (Box 10:, Folder 367)
  - Student Participation in University Governance, undated (Box 10:, Folder 368)
  - Student personnel, 1949-1951 (Box 10:, Folder 369)
  - Student personnel office, 1971-1974 (Box 10:, Folder 370)
  - Student Senate, 1949-1973 (Box 10:, Folder 371-373)
  - Student welfare committee, undated (Box 10:, Folder 374)
  - Study Abroad, undated (Box 10:, Folder 375)
  - TAFS Committee, 1971-1984 (Box 10:, Folder 376-380)
  - Teaching Award, undated (Box 10:, Folder 381)
  - Teaching-Learning Committee, 1973 (Box 10:, Folder 382)
  - Tenure, Promotion, and Reappointment procedures, 1074-1975 (Box 10:, Folder 383)
  - Trustee/Faculty Dinner Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 10:, Folder 384)
  - Uconn Club, 1971 (Box 10:, Folder 385)
  - UKAESS Newsletter, undated (Box 10:, Folder 386)
  - Vice President for Health Affairs search, 1979 (Box 10:, Folder 387)
  - Western Civilization Grant, 1984-1987 (Box 10:, Folder 388)
  - Women's History, undated (Box 10:, Folder 389)
  - Work Study, undated (Box 10:, Folder 390)